This right here is a picture of Carl Linnaeus, and I'm sure I'm mispronouncing the word.
And he's a Swedish gentleman who lived in the 1700's.
And he's known as the Father of Modern Taxonomy.
And the word taxonomy, if you just split it up into it's original root, it really is the science of really classifying things.
But when people talk about taxonomy, in this particular in Carl Linnaeus' case,
they're talking about the classification of living things.
So, classifying... classifying, organisms.
And his real innovation, before he came about, people realized that you had species of animals
that lions had certain properties that made them all lions, and they could interbreed and things like that
monkey or chimpanzees would all interbreed and that would be a separate species
and that polar bears were a separate species, and that humans were a separate species.
But what he really brought to the table, is he decided, well "Let me just not just group animals into species,
maybe I can group species into, into other categories and that's where we get the genus from...
You group similar species into a genus.
And then he went even beyond that, because even the idea of grouping things into a genus
dated back to the Ancient Greeks. He said, "Well, why don't I group similar genuses together,
into orders, orders together into classes, and then classes together into kingdoms.
So, really, what he did is, he said, "Well, maybe I can classify, I can create a tree. I can create a tree of life.
I can create a structure so we can really see how far apart any two organisms are."
And that's really why he's the Father of Modern Taxonomy.
And he did not have many tools. All he could do was look at the powers, his powers of observation.
He said, "OK, those kinds of animals, they have fur, or they reproduce in this way, or
they lay eggs, or they don't lay eggs,
or they have spinal columns, or they don't have spinal columns.
So that's the best that he could do, when he did his taxonomy.
But since then, there's obviously been tons of innovations and how we perceive animals
or the natural world, and our tools for studying them.
So one thing that he did not know about is evolution.
This idea of common ancestry and between our understandings of evolution
and our ability to look back at the fossil record,
that helps us get more precise at figuring out which animals are related to which.
We can see, "Do they have a common ancestor, more recent, or further back?"
And what even Charles Darwin didn't have, which we now use as a tool in taxonomy,