I think we have a respectable
sense of how muscles contract
on the molecular level.
Let's take a step back now and
just understand how muscles
look, at least structurally, or
how they relate to things
that we normally associate
with muscles.
So let me draw a flexing
bicep right here.
That's their elbow and
let's say that's
their hand right there.
So this is their bicep
and it's flexing.
I think we've all seen diagrams
of what muscles look,
at least on kind of a macro
level and it's connected to
the bones at either end.
Let me draw the bones.
I'm not going to detail where--
so it's connected to
the bones at either
end by tendons.
So this right here would
be some bone.
Right there would be another
bone that it's connected to.
And then this is tendons, which
connects the bones to
the muscles.
We have the general sense--
connected to two bones, when
it contracts it moves some part
of our skeletal system.
So we're actually focused
on skeletal muscles.
The other types are smooth
muscles and cardiac muscles.
Cardiac muscles are those, as
you can imagine, in our heart.
And smooth muscles are-- these
are more involuntary, slow
moving muscles and things like
our digestive tract.
And I'll do video on that in
the future, but most of the
time when people say muscles,
we associate them with
skeletal muscles that move our
skeletal system around, allow
us to run and lift and talk
and do and bite things.
So this is what we normally
associate-- let's dig in a
little bit deeper here.
So if I were to take a cross
section of this bicep right
there-- if I were to take a
cross section of that muscle
right there-- so let
me do it big.
And then it looks something
like this.
This is the inside of this
muscle over here.
Now I said back here,
we had our tendon.
And then there's actually a
covering; there's no strict
demarcation or dividing line
between the tendon and the
covering around this muscle,
but that covering is called
the epimysium and it's really
just connective tissue that
covers the muscle, kind of
protects it, reduces friction
between the muscle and the
surrounding bone and other
tissue that might be in this
person's arm right there.
And then within this muscle, you
have connective tissue on
the inside.
Let me do it in another color.
I'll do it in orange.
This is called a perimyseum,
and that's also just
connective tissue inside
of the actual muscle.
And then each of these things
that the perimysium is
dividing off-- let me say if we
were to take one of these
things and allow it to go a
little bit further-- so if we
were to take this thing right
here-- what this perimysium is
dividing off-- and if we were to
pull it out-- actually, let
me do this one right here.
If we were to pull this one out
just like that-- so you
have the perimysium surrounding
it, right?
This is all perimysium, and
it's just a fancy word for
connective tissue.
There's other stuff in there.
You could have nerves and you
could have capillaries, all
sorts of stuff because you have
to get blood and neuronal
signals to your muscles of
entry so it's not just
connective tissue.
It's other things that have to
be able to eventually get to
your muscle cells.
So each of these-- I guess you'd
call it subfibers, but
these are pretty big subfibers
of the muscle.
This is called a fascicle.
The connective tissue inside of
the fascicle is called the
endomysium.
So once again, more connective
tissues, has capillaries in
it, has nerves in it, all of
the things that have to
eventually come in contact
with muscle cells.
We're inside of a
single muscle.
All this green connective
tissue is endomysium.
And each of these things that
are in the endomysium are an
actual muscle cell.
This is an actual muscle cell.
I'll do it in purple.
So this thing right here-- I can
pull it out a little bit.
If I pull this out, this is
an actual muscle cell.
This is what we wanted to get
to, but we're going to go even
within the muscle cell to see,
understand how all the myosin
and the actin filaments fit
into that muscle cell.
So this right here is a muscle
cell or a myofiber.
The two prefixes you'll see
a lot when dealing with
muscles-- you're going to see
myo, which you can imagine
refers to muscle.
And you're also going to see
the word sarco, like
sarcolemma, or sarcoplasmic
reticulum.
So you're also go see the
prefix sarco and that's
flesh-- so sarcophagus-- or you
can think of other things
that start with sarco.
So sarco is flesh.
Muscle is flesh and
myo is muscle.
So this is myofiber.
This is an actual muscle cell
and so let's zoom in on the
actual muscle.
So let me actually draw it
really a lot bigger here.
So an actual muscle cell
is called a myofiber.
It's called a fiber because it's
longer than it is wide
and they come in various--
let me draw the
myofiber like this.
I'll take a cross section of
the muscle cell as well.
And these can be relatively
short-- several hundred
micrometers-- or it could be
quite long-- at least quite
long by cellular standards.
We're talking several
centimeters.
Think of it as a cell.
That's quite a long cell.
Because it's so long,
it actually has to
have multiple nucleuses.
Actually, to draw the nucleuses,
let me do a better
job drawing the myofiber.
I'm going to make little lumps
in the outside membranes where
the nucleuses can fit
on this myofiber.
Remember, this is just one of
these individual muscle cells
and they're really long so they
have multiple nucleuses.
Let me take its cross section
because we're going to go
inside of this muscle cell.
So I said it's multinucleated.
So if we kind of imagine its
membrane being transparent,
there'd be one nucleus over
here, another nucleus over
here, another nucleus
over here, another
nucleus over there.
And the reason why it's
multinucleated is so that over
large distances, you don't have
to wait for proteins to
get all the way from this
nucleus all the way over to
this part of the muscle cell.
You can actually have the DNA
information close to where it
needs to be.
So it's multinucleated.
I read one-- I think it was 30
or so nucleuses per millimeter
of muscle tissue is what
the average is.
I don't know if that's actually
the case, but the
nucleuses are kind of right
under the membrane of the
muscle cell-- and you remember
what that's called from the
last video.
The membrane of the muscle
cell is the sarcolemma.
These are the nucleuses.
And then if you take the cross
section of that, there are
tubes within that called
myofibrils.
So here there's a bunch
of tubes inside
of the actual cell.
Let me pull one of them out.
So I've pulled out one
of these tubes.
This is a myofibril.
And if you were to look at this
under a light microscope,
you'll see it has little
striations on it.
the striations will look
something like that, like
that, like that, and there'll
be little thin ones
like that, like that.
And inside of these myofibrils
is where we'll find our myosin
and actin filaments.
So let's zoom in over here
on this myofibril.
We'll just keep zooming until we
get to the molecular level.
So this myofibril, which is--
remember, it's inside of the
muscle cell, inside
of the myofiber.
The myofiber is a muscle cell.
Myofibral is a-- you can view
it as a tube inside of the
muscle cell.
These are the things that
are actually doing the
contraction.
So if I were to zoom in on a
myofibril, you're going to see
it-- it's going to look
something like that and it's
going to have those
bands in it.
So the bands are going to look
something like this.
You're going to have these
short bands like that.
Then you're going to have wider
bands like that, like
these little dark-- trying my
best to draw them relatively
neatly and there could be a
little line right there.
Then the same thing
repeats over here.
So each of these units of
repetition is called a sarcomere.
And these units of repetition go
from one-- this is called a
Z-line to another Z-line.
And all of this terminology
comes out of when people just
looked under a microscope and
they saw these lines, they
started attaching names to it.
And just so you have the other
terminology-- we'll talk about
how this relates to the myosin
and the actin in a second.
This right here is the A-band.
And then this distance right
here or these parts right
here, these are called
the I-bands.
And we'll talk about really in a
few seconds how that relates
to the mechanisms or the units
that we talked-- or the
molecules that we talked about
in the last video.
So if you were to zoom in here,
if you were to go into
these myofibrils, if you were
to take a cross section of
these myofibrils, what you'll
find is-- if you were to cut
it up, maybe slice it-- if you
were slice it parallel to the
actual screen that you're
looking at, you're going to
see something like this.
So this is going to
be your Z-band.
This is your next Z-band.
So I'm zooming in on
sarcomere now.
This is another Z-band.
Then you have your
actin filaments.
Now we're getting to that
molecular level
that I talked about.
And then in between the actin
filaments, you have your
myosin filaments.
Remember, the myosin filaments
had those two heads on them.
They each have two heads like
that, that crawl along the
actin filaments.
I'm just drawing a couple of
them and then they're attached
at the middle just like that.
We'll talk about in a second
what happens when the muscle
actually contracts.
And I could draw it
again over here.
So it has many more heads than
what I'm drawing, but this
just gives you an idea
of what's happening.
These are the myosin, I guess,
proteins and they all
intertwined like we saw in the
previous video and then
there'll be another
one over here.
I don't have to draw
in detail.
So you can see immediately that
the A-band corresponds to
where we have our myosin.
So this is our A-band
right here.
And there is an overlap.
They do overlap each other, even
in the resting state, but
the I-band is where you
only have actin
filaments, no myosin.
And then the myosin filaments
are held in place by titin,
which you can kind of imagine
as a springy protein.
I want to do it in a different
color than that.
So the myosin is held
in place by titin.
It's attached to the
Z-band by titin.
So what happened?
So we have all of these-- when
a neuron excites-- so let me
draw an endpoint of a neuron
right here, the endpoint of an
axon of a neuron right there.
It's a motor neuron.
It's telling this
guy to contract.
You have the action potential.
The action potential travels
along the membrane, really in
all directions.
And then it eventually, if we
look at it from this view,
they have those little
transverse or T-tubules.
They essentially go into the
cell and continue to propagate
the action potential.
Those trigger the sarcoplasmic
reticulum to release calcium.
The calcium attaches to the
troponin that's attached to
these actin filaments that moves
the tropomyosin out of
the way, and then the
crawling can occur.
The myosin can start
using ATP to crawl
along these actin filaments.
And so as you can imagine, as
they crawl along, their power
stroke is going to push-- you
can either view it as the
actin filaments in that way or
you can say that the myosin is
going to want to move in that
direction, but you're pulling
on both sides of
a rope, right?
So the myosin is going to stay
in one place and the actin
filaments are going to
be pulled together.
And that's essentially how the
muscle is contracting.
So we've, hopefully, in this
video, connected the big
picture from the flexing muscle
all the way over here
to exactly what's happening at
the molecular level that we
learned in the last
few videos.
And you can imagine, when this
happens to all of the
myofibrils inside of the muscle,
right, because the
sarcoplasmic reticulum's
releasing calcium generally
into the cytoplasm of-- which
is also called myoplasm,
because we're dealing with
muscle cells-- the cytoplasm
of this muscle cell.
The calcium floods all
of these myofibrils.
It's able to attach to all of
the troponin-- or at least a
lot of the troponin on top of
these actin filaments and then
the whole muscle contracts.
And then when that's done, each
muscle fiber, myofiber,
or each muscle cell
will not have that
much contracting power.
But when you couple it with all
of them that are around
it-- if you just have one,
actually, working, or a few of
them, you'll just
have a twitch.
But if you have all of them
contracting together, then
that's actually going to create
the force to actually
do some work, or actually pull
your bones together, or lift
some weights.
So hopefully you found
that mildly useful.