After being done with glycolysis and the Kreb's Cycle,
we're left with 10 NADHs and 2 FADH2s
and I told you that these are going to be used in the Electron Transport Chain
and they're all sitting in the matrix of our mitochondria
and I said that they're going to be used in the
Electron Transport Chain in order to actually generate ATP.
So that's what I'm going to focus on in this video--the Electron Transport Chain.
And just so you know, a lot of this stuff is known,
but some of the details are actually current areas of research.
People have models and they're trying to substantiate
the models, but things are happening at such a small
scale here, that people can just look at the evidence, some
of it of which is indirect, and say this is probably
what's happening. Most of this is very well established,
but some of the exact mechanisms--for example--how exactly some of the proteins work--
aren't completely understood. So I think it's very important
for you to understand that this is kind of at the cutting edge.
You're already there.
So the basic idea here is that the NADHs--and that's where
I'll focus--FADH2 is kind of the same idea, although
it's electrons are at a slightly lower energy state, so they
won't produce quite as many ATPs. Each NADH--maybe I'll write it here--
each NADH is going to be, as you'll see, indirectly responsible
for the production of three ATPs, and each
FADH2, in a very efficient cell, in both of these cases,
will be indirectly responsible for the production of 2 ATPs.
And the reason why this guy produces fewer ATPs
is because the electrons that he has going into the Electron
Transport Chain are at a slightly lower energy level
than the ones from NADH.
So in general, I just said indirectly, how does this whole business work?