In the last video, we got an
overview of electrotonic
potentials and action potentials
and how they
essentially can transmit
potential differences through
a cell or how they can
move a potential
difference through a cell.
And just as a bit of review,
electrotonic is if you have
some type of charge disruption--
let's say a
sodium gate opens and a bunch of
positive ions flow in, that
very quickly is going to
make things nearby
more positive, right?
It's very quickly because the
positive charges are going to
move away from their
positive brethren.
Positives and positives
repel each other.
And so if we go some point
further off in the cell--
let's say we were looking at
that point right here-- the
positive charges-- if there's
a positive charge here, it's
going to want to move
in that direction.
If you have a positive charge
here, it's going to move in
this direction.
So it's going to become more
positive very quickly.
So that's what we talk about
electrotonic potential.
And the benefit is, it happens
very, very quickly.
If we're looking at this
point, as soon as these
positive charges move in, a
positive charge here that's
right there is going to want to
move there and a positive
charge that's here is going to
want to move to the right, but
not as quickly because the the
effect gets diffused, right?
The impact on this charge is
less than this charge because
it's further away.
And we could think more, we
could run computer simulations
about it, but I think you
get the general idea.
Positive things flow in.
Other positive things
want to move away.
That makes any point that's some
distance away from that
disruption a little bit more
positive so it'll affect its
voltage almost immediately.
So it's very fast, but
the problem is it
dissipates with distance.
If we go really far from that--
if we went all the way
down here, this guy would have
almost no impact from what's
happening at this opening
of this sodium gate.
So that's its negative.
On the other hand, on the other
side of the spectrum, we
looked at action potentials.
Action potentials
are all about--
you have some stimulus.
In general, it's getting a
little bit of a positive
charge near a sodium gate.
So normally, we're resting
at minus 70 millvolts.
Maybe you have a little bit of
a positive charge come, maybe
through some type of
electrotonic interaction, but
that's not enough.
But maybe another one comes by
and it gets you to minus 55
millvolts and then the gate
opens, sodium floods in, we
become much more positive.
Then the sodium gates close.
Potassium gates open.
The potassium wants to flow out
of the cell because we're
positive in the cell now and
there's a lot of potassium on
the inside because of the
sodium potassium pumps.
So then we go back
to negative.
We actually overshoot.
And just in case you want to
know, at this point, we're
kind of in this refractory
period.
And the original gate that just
opened and closed-- it's
deactivated for a short
period of time.
So there's some period of time
that another stimulus won't be
able to do it, but then our
sodium potassium pumps can get
us back to normal.
But the whole time that that
was happening, as the gate
that was to the left got all
charged up, as the sodium
started flowing in, it's
obviously going to make it a
little bit more positive to the
gate that's directly to
the right of it.
So the gate that's to the right
of it, its charge is
going to go slightly up and
then bam, it hits its
threshold for firing.
So then that sodium gate opens
and the same thing happens a
little bit further
to the right.
And I could keep doing that,
maybe even a little bit
further to right.
A gate's potential might look
something like that and that's
how it travels.
Now the benefit of this is that
the signal never loses
strength, right?
We can just keep going down
the cell like this.
We could do that for millions
of miles if we had to.
The negative is that it's slower
than electrotonic in
that you have to open and close
these gates and it also
requires energy because you're
always having to re-balance
the charge potential between
the inside and the
outside of the cell.
So we need to think about, how
could a cell use both of these
things to optimize those
tradeoffs between signal
dissipation and speed?
And this is exactly what
the neuron does do.
So let's go back.
Now we're ready to close the
loop and actually talk about
the neuron.
So when I talked about a neuron
getting excited on the
dendrite-- if I zoom in on a
dendrite-- let's say this is a
dendrite's membrane
right here.
Let me zoom in on a dendrite.
So that's the dendrite
right there.
Let's say that this
is a drawing of
that point right there.
When I say stimulated, what's
happening is, some channel is
being triggered, some gate
is being opened.
And so let's say that this is
a sodium channel and it
stimulates-- the stimulus, it
could be-- like in our action
potential-- it could
be voltage gated.
A higher voltage might
cause it to happen.
It might be some chemical
stimulus from some other
terminal end of some
other axon.
It could be pressure.
It could be, who knows?
It could be some molecule that
stimulates it, but something
is making a gate open and maybe
it's a sodium gate and
so positive charge is going
to flood in here.
Positive charge is going
to flow into the cell.
We know why it does that.
There's a lot of sodium
on the outside.
That's what the sodium
potassium pump does.
So positive charge flows
into the cell.
So immediately, it's going
to have some impact.
If we measure the voltage here,
immediately the positive
charge here is going to want
to travel away and so this
point is going to become a
little bit more positive.
If we look at this point, it's
going to become a little bit
more positive, but it's so far
away from the original
reaction that maybe it doesn't
become as positive because the
ions are becoming dissipated
as we go through the cell.
So as we go right here
to our axon hillock,
we have more gates.
Let's say that that's
a sodium gate.
Let's say that this is
a potassium gate.
Let's say that we have
another sodium gate.
Doesn't have to be configured
this way.
We have another potassium
gate right there.
Now if we just had one event
here, we're so far away from
that event that maybe if we
measured the potential at that
point, at the axon hillock--
remember, that's the little
bulge that turns
into the axon.
Let's do that same chart that
I had before, where we have
membrane potential.
So potential across
the membrane.
And then we have time.
So if we look at this point--
let's say we're looking at
this point right here, that
point and we're comparing it
to the outside of
the membrane.
So it's starting at minus
70 millivolts.
That's its resting.
And let's say that some event
happened out here and
electrotonically it's going to
increase the potential a
little bit because positive
charge is going to make its
way and they're all going
to push each other.
They're all going to get away
from each other and this one's
going to become slightly
positive.
But let's say it only goes to
minus 65, nothing happens.
Then your sodium potassium
pumps come into effect so
nothing really happened.
It didn't trigger the neuron,
but let's say that gets
stimulated again and let's say
there's a couple more that get
stimulated and their combined
effects-- because all of them
are flooding with positive
ions now-- their combined
effects are enough to get this
point to the threshold.
So they're enough to get
this point to minus 55.
And we know what's going
to happen here.
As soon as this sodium gate gets
to minus 55, it's going
to open up.
It's going to open up and sodium
is going to flood in.
Sodium is going to flood in
until we get to positive 40.
then it's going to close.
Then the potassium gate's going
to open and get us back
to where we were before.
We're going to overshoot a
little bit and then our sodium
potassium pump's going to get
back to where we wanted.
That's going to happen there,
but as the sodium is floating
in into that first gate, this
guy's going to become positive
here and then this gate, this
sodium gate, is going to
become triggered.
And this is that action
potential idea.
Now, we could just keep going
our action potential all the
way down the axon because we
said the benefit of the
electrotonic is that it goes
fast, but doesn't cover a lot
of distance.
This is a relatively short
distance, while the axon is
super-long.
So you might say, OK, I see,
electrotonic from the dendrite
to the axon hillock-- and then
we use action potential all
the way down the axon.
That would be reasonable because
we're not going to
lose our signal strength.
We would keep having that
domino, that chain reaction
going all the way until we get
to our terminal end, but the
problem there is, it's slow.
I mean, if this is a five foot
long axon, I don't want to
have a slow signal.
If someone just bit me, I
want to move my hand.
If I just touched a stove, I
want to move my hand quickly.
I don't want all that signal
to take so much time, all
these gates to open and close
along the whole four or five
feet-- of if I'm a dinosaur,
move my arm.
It needs to happen quickly.
So what happens is that
there's a combination.
You get your signal and this
amplifies the signal.
The signal is very
weak here, right?
It only got us to minus 55,
but then when that first
sodium gate opens, it creates a
huge positive potential that
opens the next gate.
So we have a huge positive
potential here.
Now the axons have these
huge spaces where
they're covered up.
They're covered up by these
Schwann cells or by these
myelin sheaths.
So even if there are
gates underneath
them, they're useless.
They can't interface with
the outside sodiums and
potassiums. So over this
distance of the axon, you
cannot have a straight-up
action potential.
What happened is, your action
potential here, it made
everything a lot more positive
than it would have been had
there not been that opening of
the gate and now you can have
an electrotonic effect again.
So you kind of boosted
your signal.
So now this might
get to plus 40.
Maybe over here we only get to
minus 50, but minus 50, once
again is enough to trigger a
sodium gate, which then makes
everything really
positive again.
It boosts the signal.
It makes everything positive
again, then your potassium
gates, everything, comes
out of the cell again.
So everything gets back
to normal, but
it boosted the signal.
Now electrotonically, this
is super positive.
Now the electrotonic effect,
if we go some distance down
the axon, this'll be less
positive, but it'll be just
enough to trigger another
action potential.
And then that happens again.
So we have this combination
of action potentials with
electrotonics.
So electrotonic-- this is very
fast. This is a fast
interaction.
It happens immediately,
but it dissipates
as it covers distance.
So we can't have these nodes
of Ranvier being super far
from each other.
They have to be just far enough
so that when one action
potential happens, that
it's still enough to
trigger the next one.
It's not going to boost its
potential to plus 40, but as
long as it boosts it to minus
55, we're still going to
produce a signal to
keep moving on.
So this is a really good
tradeoff because we get fast,
slow, but it boosts
the signal.
Fast signal dies down, but it's
enough to essentially
trigger this guy and then
it boosts the signal.
It's slow, but then we
travel fast again.
Signal dies, boosts the signal
slow, and we keep traveling
that way down the axon.
And this is actually called
a saltatory conduction.
Let me write this down.
Saltatory conduction, which
I think comes from
the Latin for hopping.
I remember when I first learned
this in biology class,
they kind of talked about it.
Somehow putting the myelin
sheath there just magically
made it happen faster and these
things just hop from one
action potential reaction
to another, but
that's not what's happening.
You're boosting the signal here
with an action potential.
When these gates open, it
becomes super positive.
When it becomes super positive
here-- from a maybe not so
positive trigger becomes super
positive, that allows this
point to become reasonably
positive, enough to trigger
the next reaction.
When that triggers, then it
becomes super positive, makes
this reasonably positive
or less negative, it
triggers the next one.
So it's a combination of action
potentials that boosts
the signal.
And electrotonic effects that
move the signal, that gives us
this saltatory conduction.
So that's actually how neurons
are able to make that tradeoff
between traveling huge
distances, but not losing
their signal.